Finding Aid for Planned Parenthood League, Inc., Records 1932-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Planned Parenthood League, Inc. 1932-1979
Planned Parenthood League, Inc. of Detroit.
(in 9 boxes)
8.5 linear feet
85386 Bj 2
Detroit, Michigan chapter of the Planned Parenthood Federation of America, founded in 1932 as the Detroit Chapter of the Michigan Birth Control League. Minutes, correspondence, reports, surveys, newsletters, and printed material document the efforts of the Planned Parenthood League to provide birth control information and services to residents of the Detroit area
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group was deposited with the library, April 30, 1982. Ownership of the records has been retained by the Planned Parenthood League. Donor no. 6613
The record group is open for research.
The Detroit Chapter of the Birth Control League of Michigan was organized in 1932, one year after the founding of the Michigan Birth Control League. There had been organized efforts to provide contraceptive information in the Detroit area in the previous decade: in 1922, Margaret Sanger had lectured on the subject; and in 1927 the Mother's Clinic opened its doors to young women desiring contraceptive information. Two additional birth control clinics were established in 1931, at Harper Hospital and Woman's Hospital.
The Detroit league underwent several name changes in the succeeding decades. In 1934, following the lead of the state league with which it was affiliated, the Detroit organization changed its name to the Detroit Chapter of the Maternal Health League of Michigan. In 1942, it became the Detroit Chapter, Michigan League for Planned Parenthood. The name was again changed in 1944, to the Detroit League for Planned Parenthood, Inc. When the Michigan maternal Health League dissolved in 1953, the Detroit league became an affiliate of Planned Parenthood Federation of America. Finally, in 1960 the Detroit and Oakland County leagues merged to form Planned Parenthood League, Inc.
In its early years the organization concentrated on operating birth control clinics and providing contraceptive information; it assumed responsibility for financing the Harper Clinic in 1933. The league soon expanded its education and publicity activities, establishing an information booth at the Michigan State Fair for the first time in 1939. In the 1940's and 1950's the league attempted to reach industrial workers by distributing leaflets through their unions and mailing brochures to women in neighborhoods served by the clinics.
Although the concept of birth control gained increasing acceptance from the 1940's onward, Planned Parenthood continued to face opposition, particularly from religious groups. It was not until 1967, after years of applying, that Planned Parenthood was finally accepted as a non-financial member of the United Community Services of metropolitan Detroit.
Population control was a major goal of the organization, but through the years Planned Parenthood broadened its program to include the goals of child spacing and maternal and child health. A project in venereal disease detection was begun in 1966; it later became a regular clinic service. In 1969 Infertility Diagnostic and Counseling Service was started and in 1971 a vasectomy service was offered. From 1969 through 1976 Planned Parenthood League received grants form the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare to be used in conjunction with the Detroit and Wayne County health departments for family planning services. In 1972 Planned Parenthood League turned the granteeship over to the Southeastern Michigan Family Planning Project (SEMFPP), a newly-formed community corporation comprised of service-providing agencies. Planned Parenthood League terminated its federal family planning grant in 1976, but maintained its clinical facilities and educational programs. While the board had voted in 1949 not to provide clinical services for "premarital women" or unwed mothers, by the 1970's the league was even targeting many of its programs toward teenagers. After the 1973 Supreme Court decision legalizing abortion, Planned Parenthood League initiated abortion counseling and referral services. Despite periodic financial crises, Planned Parenthood League continued through the 1970's to provide sex education, reproductive health care information, and medical services, and to work toward its goal of gaining universal acceptance of the notion of family planning.
The Planned Parenthood League, Inc., records dates from 1932 to 1979 and measure 8.5 linear feet. The records are arranged in eight series:
Histories (1943-1949)
Board of Directors Records (1932-1979)
Committee Records (1959-1978)
Correspondence and Memoranda (1966-1979)
Medical Material (1932-1978)
Planned Parenthood Federation of America (1954-1978)
Michigan Organizations and Agencies (1965-1978)
Printed Material (1936, 1971-1978).
The minutes, correspondence, reports, surveys, newsletters, and printed material document the efforts of the Planned Parenthood League to provide birth control information and services to residents of the Detroit area and reflect the changing emphasis of the programs over the years. From its almost exclusive concentration on provision of contraceptive clinical services in its early years, Planned Parenthood came to offer such diverse programs as infertility counseling, a vasectomy service, sex education for teenagers and venereal disease detection. Correspondence with pharmaceutical companies in the 1960's and 1970's reflects the participation of Planned Parenthood League in tests of contraceptives, particularly oral contraceptives. Clinic surveys and statistical reports, along with information contained in annual reports (filed for the most part with board of directors minutes) document the medical services provided by the League.
Subjects:
Abortion--Michigan--Detroit.; Birth control--Michigan--Detroit.; Planned Parenthood Federation of America.; Women--Michigan--Detroit--Societies and clubs.; Planned Parenthood League, Inc. (Detroit, Mich.)
- Histories 1943-1949
  Histories (1943-1949) consists of several short histories of the Detroit league and of the Michigan Birth Control League.
  - Story of Birth Control in Michigan 1922-1943 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1949, Undated (Box 1)
- Board of Directors 1959-1978
  The Board of Directors Records (1959-1978) consist primarily of minutes of meetings of the board of directors and of the executive committee, which are filed together for the years 1932 to 1965 and in two separate subseries for the years 1966 to 1978. Also included are scattered minutes and committee reports of annual meetings and several annual reports.
  - Minutes 1932-1965 (includes interfiled Executive Committee minutes), 19 folders (Box 1)
  - Minutes 1966-1976 (Box 2)
  - Minutes 1977 (Box 3)
  - Minutes (Executive Committee) 1966-1978, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Annual Meetings, 1960-1961,1963 1965-1978), 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Annual Reports 1968-1977, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Members and officers, 1958 1962-1979 (Box 3)
  - Handbook 1975 (Box 3)
  - Training Guides (Box 3)
- Committee Records 1959-1978
  Committee Records (1959-1978) consist of scattered minutes of committee meetings, dating primarily from the late 1960's and 1970's. A more complete account of the activities of the various committees, however, is contained in reports presented at board meetings and filed with board of directors minutes.
  - Membership Lists 1974-1977 (Box 3)
  - Budget and Finance Committee 1972 (Box 3)
  - Information and Education Committee 1965 (Box 4)
  - Legal Advisory Committee 1968-1970 (Box 4)
  - Medical Advisory Committee, 1965 1968-1978, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Ministerial Advisory Committee 1959-1967, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Nominating Committee, 1965-1974 1976-1978, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Nurses and Social Workers Advisory Committee 1965 (Box 4)
  - Personnel Committee 1970-1976, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Personnel Manual, 1969 1971-1973, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Planning Committee 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - Policy and Review Committee 1977 (Box 4)
  - Resources Committee 1977 (Box 4)
  - Search Committee for Executive Director 1978 (Box 4)
  - Site Search Committee December 1974-November 1976 (Box 4)
  - Volunteer Committee 1965 (Box 4)
- Correspondence and Memoranda 1966-1979
  Correspondence and Memoranda (1966-1979) consists of carbon copies of outgoing correspondence and of internal memoranda of Planned Parenthood League officials with staff members. Included are memoranda of Howard Lischeron, who was executive director from 1974 to 1977, and of Virginia Jones, who was assistant director. The fiftieth anniversary folder contains a booklet on the history of Planned Parenthood League entitled Courageous Crusade.
  - Correspondence 1966-March 1975, 8 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence April 1975-1979, 11 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence re 50th Anniversary of Planned Parenthood League 1972 (Box 5)
  - Memoranda of Planned Parenthood League officials 1966-1968, 1974-1978, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Memoranda: Virginia Jones 1975 (Box 5)
  - Memoranda: Howard Lischeron 1974-1977, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Memoranda: Medical Director 1975-1976 (Box 5)
  - Memoranda and Notes: Business Manager 1975-1976 (Box 5)
- Medical Material 1932-1978
  Medical Material (1932-1978) consists of three subseries: medical grants, clinic reports, and Department of Health, Education and Welfare applications. The medical grants subseries contains correspondence with pharmaceutical companies in the 1960's and 1970's regarding studies of contraceptives conducted at Planned Parenthood League clinics. Clinic reports includes statistical reports and surveys of clinic services. The HEW applications, which are filed in approximate chronological order, include proposals, budgets, and correspondence relating to the applications for funding, as well as evaluations of the programs that were conducted under the grants.
  - Medical Grants
    - Eli Lilly and Company 1962-1968, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - McNeil Laboratories, Inc. 1968 (Box 6)
    - Mead Johnson Research Center 1963-1968 (Box 6)
    - Ortho Research Foundation 1963-1974, 1977, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Parke Davis and Company 1962-1971, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Schering Corporation 1968 (Box 6)
    - G.D. Searle and Company 1960-1969 (Box 6)
    - The Quibb Institute 1965-1968 (Box 6)
    - Syntex 1964-1967, 1970 1978 (Box 6)
    - The Upjohn Company 1963-1970, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Wyeth Laboratories 1964-1974 (scattered) (Box 6)
  - Clinic Reports
    - 1932-1953 (scattered) (Box 6)
    - Monthly 1963-1967 (Box 6)
    - Annual 1955-1970 (Box 6)
    - Social Agency Referrals from a Planned Parenthood Clinic 1949-1950 (Box 6)
    - Survey of Clinics 1949 (Box 6)
    - Medical Grant costs 1968 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence 1966-1967 (Box 6)
    - Pill Purchase Plan 1970 (Box 6)
  - Department of Health, Education, and Welfare Applications
    - Detroit General Hospital 1968-1969, 1971, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Proposal 1968 (folders 1-2) (Box 6)
    - Proposal 1968 (folder 3) (Box 7)
    - Incomplete Final Proposal 1969 (Box 7)
    - Proposal 1970 (Box 7)
    - Proposal (General) 1969-1971 (Box 7)
    - Family Planning Project 1969-1971, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Task Force 1971, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Special Meeting of Executive Council August 20, 1971 (Box 7)
    - Budget Narrative 1972 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence 1972-1976 (Box 7)
    - Audit Control 1975 (Box 7)
    - Cost Reporting Requirements 1975 (Box 7)
    - Funding 1975 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous 1975 (Box 7)
    - Planned Parenthood League Reorganization Plan 1975, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Nondiscrimination 1976 (Box 7)
    - Evaluation of Publicly Funded Family Planning Programs in Michigan 1971-1972, 1976 (Box 7)
    - Southeastern Michigan Family Planning Project, Inc. 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - Southeastern Michigan Family Planning Project-Health, Education, and Welfare Health Service Funding Regulations 1975 (Box 7)
- Planned Parenthood Federation of America 1954-1978
  Planned Parenthood Federation of America material (1954-1978) includes newsletters and memoranda from Planned Parenthood Federation of America and its research division, the Alan Guttmacher Institute. There isin addition, correspondence of Planned Parenthood League officials with other Planned Parenthood Federation of America affiliates.
  - Board of Director's Hand Book 1954 (Box 7)
  - Planned Parenthood-World Population
    - General 1962-1970 (Box 7)
    - National Medical Committee 1970-1973 (Box 7)
  - Alan Guttmacher Institute 1974-1977, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Regional Affiliates
    - Regional Task Force 1975 (Box 8)
    - Great Lakes Region
      - Great Lakes Regional Council
        - General 1970-1977, 7 folders (Box 8)
        - Rules of Procedure 1974 (Box 8)
      - Great Lakes Regional Office: Correspondence 1974-1977 (Box 8)
      - Affiliate Profile 1974-1975 (Box 8)
      - Consultant Request Forms 1974 (Box 8)
      - Data Sheet on Affiliates 1974 (Box 8)
      - Executive Director's Council 1975-1977 (Box 8)
      - Public Information and Education Committee 1973-1975 (Box 8)
      - Regional Conferences
        - 1976 (Box 8)
        - Cleveland (Box 8)
        - 1977 (Box 8)
        - Detroit 1975-1977, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Great Lakes Coalition Meeting with Regional Congressional Delegation 1975 (Box 8)
      - Great Lakes News, 1973-1977 (Box 8)
      - Illinois 1967-1978 (scattered) (Box 8)
      - Indiana 1969-1977 (Box 8)
      - Kentucky 1971, 1975-1977 (Box 8)
      - Michigan
        - Michigan Planned Parenthood Affiliates 1968, 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Michigan Planned Parenthood Council 1972-1977, 3 folders (Box 8)
        - Planned Parenthood of Flint 1964-1977 (scattered) (Box 9)
        - Planned Parenthood Association of Kalamazoo 1967-1977 (scattered) (Box 9)
        - Planned Parenthood Association of Kent County 1967-1977 (scattered) (Box 9)
        - Planned Parenthood League of Monroe County 1965-1967 (Box 9)
        - Muskegon Area Planned Parenthood 1977 (Box 9)
        - Northern Michigan Planned Parenthood 1976 (Box 9)
        - Planned Parenthood Association of Saginaw 1967-1968 (Box 9)
        - Planned Parenthood Association of Southwestern Mich. 1965-1967 (Box 9)
        - Washtenaw County League for Planned Parenthood 1966-1977 (Box 9)
      - Ohio 1966-1977 (Box 9)
      - Wisconsin 1966-1977 (scattered) (Box 9)
    - Mid-Atlantic Region 1966-1977 (scattered) (Box 9)
    - Mideast Region 1966-1966 (Box 9)
    - Northeast Region 1967-1978 (Box 9)
    - Southeast Region 1966-1977 (scattered) (Box 9)
    - Southwest Region 1968-1977 (scattered) (Box 9)
    - Western Region 1966-1977 (scattered) (Box 9)
- Michigan Organizations and Agencies 1936-1978
  The Michigan Organizations and Agencies series (1936-1978) contains correspondence and reports regarding various family planning programs and health agencies in Michigan.
  - Center for Population Planning, University of Michigan
    - General 1965-1967 (Box 9)
    - Wayne County Postpartum Family Planning Program 1966-1967 (Box 9)
    - Job Survey of Family Planning Professionals 1969-1970 (Box 9)
    - Conference on Family Planning in Michigan 1974-1975 (Box 9)
  - Detroit Medical and Surgical Center 1970-1971 (Box 9)
  - Mayor's Committee for Human Resources Development, Detroit 1968-1972 (Box 9)
  - Michigan Conference on Family Planning 1968 (Box 9)
  - Family Planning Services in Michigan 1975 (Box 9)
  - Michigan Department of Health: Division of Maternal and Child Health 1965-1974 (scattered) (Box 9)
  - Statewide Health Coordinating Council 1977-1978 (Box 9)
  - Macomb County Community Mental Health Services 1976-1977 (Box 9)
  - Oakland County Community Mental Health Services Board 1967 (Box 9)
- Printed Material 1936, 1971-1978
  Printed Material (1936, 1971-1978) includes a 1936 annual report of the maternal Health League of Michigan with a note on activities of the Detroit chapter; newsletters of Planned Parenthood League; and brochures and articles about birth control and family planning published by Planned Parenthood League, Planned Parenthood Federation of America, and related organizations.
  - Maternal Health League of Michigan 1936 (Box 9)
  - PPL News, 1971 (Box 9)
  - Peon Press, vols. I-III, 1975-1978, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - PPL (Planned Parenthood League) (Box 9)
  - General (Box 9)